Finding Aid for DeHull Travis Papers 1909-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
DeHull Travis Papers 1909-1960
Travis, DeHull N., 1882-1960.
Secretary to Michigan governor Chase S. Osborn, later assistant to the secretary general of the Nuremberg Medical Trial, 1946-1947. Correspondence, writings, and International Military Tribunal files; also photographs.
86226 Ac Aa 2
1 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was given to the library in April 1963 by Katharine Travis (donor no. 4019 ).
The collection is open for research.
DeHull Norman Travis, a Michigan attorney, was born on November 11, 1882 in Kalamazoo, Michigan. He attended the University of Michigan, where he was active in the Friars and Comedy Club. After receiving his law degree in 1908, Travis went into private practice in Flint, Michigan. In 1911, Travis served as personal secretary to Governor Chase S. Osborn. As Travis desired to return to his Flint law practice, he resigned and was appointed by Osborn to the Michigan Pardon Board for 1911-1914 (chairman, 1914). From 1918-1919, Travis again interrupted his practice to serve as publicity director for the theater division of the War Department Commission on Training Camp Activities.
In 1926, Travis moved his practice to Detroit where he also became a professor of corporate law at the University of Detroit (1926-1927) and assistant prosecuting attorney for Wayne County (1927).
During World War II, Travis served with the Intelligence Section of the U.S. Army Air Forces (October 1943-June 1944), as legal adjudicator with the U.S. Veterans Administration (1944-1946), associate counsel in the Office of U.S. Counsel for War Crimes (July-December 1946), and as assistant secretary general for International Military Tribunal I, the Medical Case (November 1946-June 1947).
After the war, Travis returned to his Detroit law practice. He died in 1960.
The papers of DeHull Norman Travis include one linear foot of material in addition to five outsize items stored separately. The collection covers the period from the start of his law practice in 1909 through his death in 1960. However, most of the collection relates to Travis's work at the Nuremberg War crimes trials.
Subjects:
Courts--United States.; Nuremberg Medical Trial, Nuremberg, Germany, 1946-1947.; Prisons--Michigan.; Travis, DeHull N., 1882-1960.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Camp Cody (N.M.); Celebrities.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Judicial proceedings.; Liberty Theater (Camp Cody, N.M.); Nuremberg Medical Trial, Nuremberg, Germany, 1946-1947.; Photographers.; Pianos.; Theatrical productions.; Travis, DeHull N., 1882-1960.; Travis family.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Contributors:
Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Clay, Lucius D. (Lucius DuBignon), 1897-1978.; Coburn, Charles Douville, 1877-1961.; Jennings, Al J.; Kuhn, Franz Christian, 1872-1926.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Millard, Frank G. (Frank Gurnee), 1897-1976.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Niezychowski, Alfred von.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Stason, E. Blythe (Edwin Blythe), 1891-1972.; Swearingen, Victor Clarence, 1899-1968.; Taylor, Telford.; Todd, Michael, 1909-1958.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Williams, G. Mennen, Mrs.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Alphabetical File
  The textual portion of the collection is arranged into a single alphabetical series of papers consisting of Awards and Ephemeral Material (one folder), Clippings (four folders), Correspondence (five folders), Genealogy, Travis Family (one folder), International Military Tribunal (fourteen folders and two large draft manuscripts), Military Entertainment (one folder), and Writings (eight folders).
  - Awards and ephemeral material (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - General 1909-1960 (Box 1)
    - International Military Tribunal (Box 1)
    - Pardon Board (Box 1)
    - Stage Productions (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    The correspondence with Governor Chase Osborn and Judges Victor Swearingen and Walter Beals, both judges at Nuremberg, is the most extensive in the Correspondence files. Although the correspondence also includes letters from Woodrow Wilson, Douglas MacArthur, Frank Murphy, Henry Ford II, G. Mennen Williams, Charles Coburn, and other notables, there is little substantive information here.
    - October 1912-December 1918, January 25-July 1928 (Box 1)
    - November 1929-December 1939 (Box 1)
    - January 1940-December 1949 (Box 1)
    - January 1950-December 1952 (Box 1)
    - January 1953-October 1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Genealogy-Travis family (Box 1)
  - International Military Tribunal
    The International Military Tribunal files are easily the most extensive portion of the collection. Though much of the material is available elsewhere, there are some important unique items. Included in the "Memoranda and Documents" folder are communications both to and from the Office of the Secretary General. "Notes" contains several pages of notes taken by Travis during the trial. "Personal Papers" includes a typewritten job description of the duties of an assistant secretary general.
    Materials of interest to researchers of the Nuremberg trials are also found elsewhere in the collection. In addition to the correspondence with Judges Beals and Swearingen, there is limited correspondence with Lucius Clay, Telford Taylor, and Judge Harold Sebring. The Writings files includes two speeches by Travis about his observations at Nuremberg. There are also materials related to Nuremberg in the Clippings files.
    - Exhibits (photocopies of several German documents) (Box 1)
    - Memoranda and Documents (Box 1)
    - Notes (Box 1)
    - Personal Papers (Box 1)
    - Printed
      - Military Tribunal, No. 1, 3, 4, 5, and General. OCC-WC Public Relations (Box 1)
      - Nuremberg Court Cartoons (by Peis) (Box 1)
      - Occupation and the Civilian's Role. U.S. Forces European Theater (Box 1)
      - These 21. Stars and Stripes (Box 1)
    - Proceedings, Military Tribunal One (The Medical Case)
      - November 21, 1946, December 1946 (Box 1)
      - January 1947 (Box 1)
      - February 1947 (Box 1)
      - March 1947 (Box 1)
      - April 1947 (Box 1)
      - May 1947 (Box 1)
      - June 1947 (Box 1)
    - Writings (not Travis)
      - Kogon, Eugen, The System of German Concentration Camps, 457 pages (Box 1)
      - Peiser, Werner. German Government and Administration 1947, 175 pages (Box 1)
  - Military entertainment 1918 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - "The Boycott of Society" (Box 1)
      (on rehabilitation of prisoners)
    - "Bubbles" (Box 1)
      (sketches of historical figures)
    - "The Cross" (Box 1)
      (a history of the Red Cross)
    - "Genocide or the Greatest Murder Cases in History" November 2, 1954 (Box 1)
      (speech on Nuremberg given at Birmingham Exchange Club)
    - "My Brother's Keeper" (Box 1)
      (on the need for charity)
    - "The Nuremberg War Crimes Trial" November 6, 1950 (Box 1)
      (speech delivered before Oakland County Bar Association)
    - "What Is It?" (Box 1)
      (on local theater clubs)
- Photographs
  The photographs series includes portraits; photos of family, political figures, and stage and screen personalities; and photos of, and relating to, the Nuremberg Medical Trial, 1946-1947.
  - Family (Box 1)
  - Informal portraits (Box 1)
  - International Military Tribunal (Box 1)
  - Political Figures (Box 1)
  - Portraits (Box 1)
  - Stage and Screen Personalities (Box 1)
  - Stage Productions and Theaters (Box 1)